Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subtitles subscription] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subtitles subscription] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Lady Sourire, what brings you here on this frosty night?
The heavy frost makes it hard for Lingrong to walk alone,
so I came to accompany her.
Sourire is an excellent zither player.
I invited her for fear that my singing would be monotonous.
Singing accompanied by the zither is naturally the best.
It's very kind of Lady Sourire to make the trip.
I wonder what songs Your Highness would like to hear.
We would offer good wishes on a such beautiful night
with blooming flowers and a full moon.
Sing a song about the fondness of love.
Yes.
As sunlight streams through the bedside folding screen,
her hair at the temples curls over her snow-white cheeks.
Sleepily she paints her eyebrows slim,
taking her time to dress and rinse.
When she puts on a flower between mirrors,
to tell her face from the flower is difficult.
The new patch on her brocade vest
is two love birds in gold thread.
Two love birds in gold thread.
[a poem by Wen Tingyun, late Tang Dynasty]
The song is very nice, but I did not hear the loving feeling in it.
Attendant An, were you being flippant with me?
Although this song doesn't mention love directly, every verse expresses a woman's joy after falling in love.
Besides, "two love birds in gold thread" symbolize conjugal love.
If so, why isn't the affection expressed in your singing?
Ah, did you feel upset seeing His Majesty staying with me?
Is that why you didn't sing well?
Your Highness, Attendant An caught a chill and has a sore throat today.
What a coincidence!
In the last few days, Attendant An sang to His Majesty all night every night.
There was nothing wrong with her throat.
- Song Zhi.
- Yes.
Bring Attendant An a glass of sweet rose wine.
This wine will dispel your cold and you can go on singing.
Yes.
Your Highness, I'm afraid I shouldn't drink
sweet or pungent things when I sing.
[scoffs] You can't sing, nor can you drink.
By rights, it was His Majesty who summoned you here.
You two may look down on me, but His Majesty...
(clearing his throat)
Since Consort Fleur awards it to you...
You should drink it.
Yes.
Now, would you sing us a nice song?
(coughs)
What's wrong? Are you all right?
(clearing his throat)
Your Majesty, Your Highness...
It is certainly beautiful when the zither is paired with beautiful singing.
However, it can also be uniquely beautiful
when the zither is paired with spoken words.
Will Your Majesty allow me?
All right.
Yes.
[Immortals at the Magpie Bridge, a poem by Qin Guan]
Above delicate clouds,ever-changing,
live two stars - the cowherd and the weaver.
"The two lovers separated by Heaven's River
grieve in silence on their annual traverse."
When autumn's gilding wind comes to the jade-like dew,
the magpies take flight to form a bridge for the two.
Tender passion flows like the River eternal;
but the bliss of union is a dream ephemeral.
How can they bear to look upon
the Magpie Bridge, their homeward road?
For a love between immortal hearts,
why need it be seen every dawn to dusk?
Isn't Lady Sourire the harem's top scholar?
All right. His Majesty and I are getting tired.
Thank you for your hard work.
- Zhou Ninghai.
- Yes, Your Highness.
Please escort them out.
Yes.
I bid Your Majesty and Your Highness goodbye.
Certainly.
Your Majesty.
It is getting late.
Time for bed.
Her Highness appreciates your hard work tonight, My Ladies.
and grants you these rewards.
I thank Her Highness.
If there is nothing else,
then allow me to to take my leave, My Ladies.
You are safe at our own place.
If you feel like crying, then let it out.
Sourire, we are not performing girls.
How can she cheapen us like this?
And even reward us with jade pendants?
How offensive!
[to reviewers: the Chinese sentence is like "What the heck is this!"]
Am I an entertainer that she tips?
My Lady!
My Lady, you have all the reasons to be mad.
But if this breaks, we can't imagine what chaos that might cause.
Don't cry.
Your throat is not well. Drink some tea to moisten it.
Sourire, you had to suffer the humiliation today with me.
But if you hadn't been there,
to spare me some face in front of His Majesty,
I can't imagine how much more mortified I would be!
His Majesty's reliance on Nian Gengyao
inflates Consort Fleur's pride.
His Majesty must see to the bigger picture,
so he wouldn't fall out with Consort Fleur for our sake.
I so wish for Nian Gengyao to leave Beijing as soon as possible
and for Consort Fleur's arrogance to be dented a little.
That won't be easy.
Even disregarding the long mutual affection between His Majesty and Consort Fleur ,
His Majesty is unlikely to snub Consort Fleur
as long as Nian Gengyao is in favor.
I went to the Palace of Earthly Honor
to inform that Your Majesty was ill in bed and wouldn't
be able to attend tomorrow's chrysanthemum assembly.
Who would have thought! Xiao-Xiazi told me that
Consort Fleur had bidden Lady Sourire and Attendant An to perform for her.
So, I stayed to look on.
When they finished and walked out,
they looked really composed as if nothing was wrong.
I know Lady Sourire is not an impetuous person by nature.
But I wouldn't have expected Attendant An to be so restrained.
I should have paid more attention to her.
That was when she was out in public.
I don't know how she would be once back in her palace.
The ability to restrain oneself is always good.
Consort Fleur has indulged her arrogance so much
that she recklessly tramples on other people's dignity.
In the end, she'll only be despised by everyone else.
Anyway, I appreciate how Attendant An's behaved.
(joyful shouting and laughter) Here! I'm here!
I am here!
These two plum branches are the best.
Be careful, My Lady!
You can't catch me!
Come on if you can catch me!
Take care, My Lady.
You won't catch me!
You can try!
My Lady, you should put on a coat.
It's cold and snowing.
I'm listening to their happy laughters.
It's something I haven't heard for a long time.
Lady Sourire and Attendant An have sent us quite a lot of coal.
I'll light the fire for you.
It doesn't matter.
The coal can warm your body, but it can't warm your heart.
My Lady, you are back.
Didn't you go to see the white plum blossoms in the courtyard?
Why are you back so soon?
I got a little dizzy from gazing at the snow.
Si Lang, your intentions to plant the white plums in the courtyard were good,
but everything becomes the same color when the snow falls.
Not a problem.
If you prefer red plum blossoms,
I'll order some trees from the
Garden of Leaning Plums to be transplanted here.
Hey!
Didn't you ask me to focus on these transcriptions?
Now you come back to distract me with your talk.
I can't believe that you blame me for your lack of concentration!
Hadn't you beated me by 3 moves in our Go game earlier,
I wouldn't have to bear your punishment now.
An emperor's words carry weight.
You can't eat your words on doing the transcriptions for me.
All right.
Huan Huan is here sewing Si Lang's winter clothes as a gift.
It's not about my promise.
Just for your sewing,
I would gladly make three transcriptions.
Si Lang, you said this yourself:
you will copy down all the plum poems for me.
Do not go back on your words.
You pasted translucent paper on the windows.
When the snow outside shines through,
it is brighter than the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
I don't like the room to be dim.
Besides, candles have to be lit when it rains or snows.
It is smelly, and also too wasteful.
You are quite frugal.
As soon as winter arrived,
the money spent on candles in the harem alone increased a lot.
Although not a large amount,
it is an expense after all.
That’s out of my small-mindedness.
It’s unexpected that Your Majesty appreciates it.
When I meet the Empress,
I will tell her this clever technique.
That would make some savings in the harem.
It's almost the end of the year.
If we can save some money to open a porridge house
for the poor, that will do more good than the candles.
Right, I will tell the Empress to do so.
Peace to Lady Chun.
Where is Sourire?
She's in chamber.
My Lady, she's with His Majesty... My Lady…
Sourire, Sourire!
Chun’er is here.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Sourire, have a look.
I picked these red plum blossoms for you. Aren't they pretty?
Yes, they are.
Sourire, it's so nice and warm here.
It is freezing outside.
Here, warm yourself by the fire.
Your Majesty, do you like the plum blossoms I picked for Sourire?
She was just nagging about red plum,
and there you are.
Well, I know my sister best.
Attendant Chun seems to have grown much taller.
Your Majesty must have forgotten that I'll be 17 after new year.
Don't just stand there and talk.
Brush off the snow quickly before you catch a cold.
Otherwise, you'd cry when you take medicine.
So much for showing us the blossoms.
I'll have them arranged in a vase.
Jinxi.
Sourire, don't you have a white porcelain vase here?
It would be best for the red plum.
You are good at picking plum blossoms.
They are still in bud.
It will take a few days before they bloom.
I like the color a lot. It warms your heart just to look at it.
For the blossoms I picked, what should you reward me, Sourire?
I don't have anything
but the new pastries my kitchen made.
Great! There is nothing better than that.
Aiya, I have to thank you for finally getting me something to eat.
Otherwise, Sourire will not feed me anything.
That’s not true.
Sourire cares for Your Majesty the most.
The only reason for Sourire to keep Your Majesty hungry
would be Your Majesty gazing at her and not having a chance to eat.
Look at her! She must have learned to sharpen her tongue from you.
Eat, the food will keep Your Majesty's mouth busy.
I am not "Your Majesty" today.
Think of me as a child from an ordinary rich family.
Can’t I be a bit garrulous?
I dare not dictate to an emperor,
but I can push around a wealthy man.
If you don't finish copying these poems,
forget about dinner tonight!
Did you hear that? Bullying me, isn't she?
She's my sister. I don't feel that way.
You have to grind the ink, or I won't write.
I was wondering why this scene looks familiar to me
when Your Majesty banters with Sourire.
Now I see. My own sister
and her husband were just like this at home.
She grinds the ink while he writes.
You ate a lot of snacks.
Drink some water.
Why don't you let her finish?
Go on.
Your Majesty loves to listen to such playful words.
My sister and her husband always have a great time
together even without exchanging a word.
My mother called it ...
Hmm...
Ah, yes! "Intimacy in the boudoir".
Where did you hear these risqué words at such a young age?
Stop talking nonsense.
And Your Majesty must stop indulging her.
Your Majesty, was I talking nonsense?
Of course not.
Your words are ... absolutely brilliant.
Huan Huan and I should be just like that.
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subtitles subscription] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
My Lady,
We are entering the Hall of Mental Cultivation in a moment.
Please do not be afraid.
(giggles)
I've served many concubines before,
but none laughed as much as you do.
Slow down. Slow down.
I noticed Lady Sourire was using translucent paper
on her windows, which saves a lot of money on candles.
What do you think?
For Beijing's long winter,
Lady Sourire's method is very useful.
It's good to save money whenever possible as the year end approaches.
I always thought that her best talents were in poetry and literature.
I overlooked her talent for household management.
I did underestimate her.
Noble Lady Sourire is intelligent and able to learn anything easily.
What's more precious is her kindness.
She wants to open a food relief center using the money saved.
She can do great things in the future.
I heard that Your Majesty called for Attendant Chun last night.
You reviewed the log of Attendance Services?
Attendant Chun has been in the harem for two years
and grown up into a lovely lady.
I remember that she had a sweet tooth
and loved to dress in bright colors.
So this morning I sent her some sweets and bright clothes.
She is light-hearted and a child at heart.
It's good for a young girl to be light-hearted,
but now she is truly a concubine.
She should be at least be more decorous and sedate.
I like her candid nature.
Unlike those having a provocative nature who upset me.
(sighs)
Your Majesty, Zhang Tingyu is here.
I'll be with him in a moment.
Yes.
Your Majesty, allow me to take my leave.
Is everything all right with Nian Gengyao in Beijing?
He is really busy entertaining guests.
It's not odd that he has some old friends in Beijing.
Your Majesty, please excuse my bluntness.
The guests are all his subordinates.
He wouldn't even look at any other officials.
Go on.
During his trip, en route to Beijing
Nian Gengyao ordered Banner General Fan Shijie
and Zhili Governor Li Weijun
to kowtow upon his arrivals and departures.
He led an ostentatious procession entering Beijing.
Officials below the Princes kneeled to receive him
while he sat impassively on the horse,
without even looking at them.
Many glanced at him sideways.
Was it really like that?
I dare not tell an untruth to Your Majesty.
As Nian Gengyao won a victory and returned in glory,
it's understandable that he felt excessive pride.
I'll warn him.
I feel reassured hearing Your Majesty's saying so.
You are burdened with much work at the Ministry of Revenue.
As Nian Gengyao is familiar with border affairs,
you can consult with him if you have any questions.
But remember, only consult.
If his subordinates aren't loyal to their posts,
and instead, abuse their power and create disturbances,
you can present a memorandum to me immediately.
I will punish them severely without leniency.
The lunar new year is around the corner.
Has the year-end bonus arrived?
Yes.
However, the Household Department said
that His Majesty ordered to reduce expenses.
So they halved the bonus this year.
I always reward the servants generously every new year.
Doubling the amount is yet short.
Half the amount is "a cup of water to a burning carriage".
Exactly.
Unlike before, the Great General will spend this new year in Beijing.
We have to give out more rewards.
If you want the Palace staff to be obedient,
you must have prestige and His Majesty’s favor.
But most importantly, it's the amount of money you reward.
That's what makes them genuinely work for you.
Perhaps Your Highness can ask the Great General for some help.
These years, my brother has both openly and secretly
given me much financial support.
Otherwise, I can’t get through even ten days
with this tiny amount of monthly stipend.
But I can't keep "holding out my hand" to my family.
Actually, it would not be difficult if Your Highness
wants to have some private earnings.
What’s your idea?
They say that since the General came back to Beijing,
flocks of people have been eager to pay him a formal visit.
Unfortunately, the Great General is too busy to see them.
These people have been as anxious as headless chickens
not knowing what to do.
If Your Highness was willing to put in a good word
to the Great General on their behalf,
they will certainly know how to pay Your Highness back.
Is that really so easy?
The imperial examination aims at selecting talents.
These people offer their services for brighter prospects.
If some of them are really good
and the General recommends them to His Majesty,
Your Highness also shares part of the merit.
His Majesty forbids the harem to be pass comment on political affairs...
If they want to see my brother,
I can certainly pass a word for them.
Whether they are selected or not, it’s up to my brother.
That is very wise, Your Highness.
My Lady, you have removed the stitches
and corrected the sewing back and forth many times.
Haven’t you finished it yet?
It’s for His Majesty. It must be done perfectly.
My Lady, you have been coughing non-stop
since you caught a cold a few days ago.
It's quite a few days since His Majesty last visited, isn't it?
More than a month.
His Majesty is either with Consort Fleur or Lady Sourire.
Consort Fleur is getting all the glory.
I can’t compete with her.
That makes sense. But when His Majesty visits Lady Sourire,
she should have reminded His Majesty to see you, My Lady.
His Majesty didn’t come.
Maybe Sourire didn’t say anything.
I heard that Attendant Chun served His Majesty recently.
She's still lively and noisy as before even after she gained favor.
Perhaps it wasn't His Majesty's intention to favor her.
It might have been the Empress's idea.
Her Majesty's always kind like that.
She’s considerate to everyone.
But Consort Fleur keeps bullying you, My Lady.
Her Majesty can hardly take care of you despite her kind heart.
My Lady, please go to rest early.
I'll bring an imperial doctor early tomorrow morning.
All right. You can go now.
Yes.
Oh,
you don’t need to make the bed for me today.
Yes.
Consort Fleur ...
Go to hell!
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
All rise and take a seat.
I thank Your Majesty.
It's been cold and very windy lately.
It is kind of you to come to greet me this early.
I was hoping to come with Lingrong,
but she's not feeling well and can't bear the wind.
So I came with Attendant Chun.
Attendant Chun is even prettier than I last saw her.
How was His Majesty to you?
His Majesty likes me a lot.
He ordered the Imperial Kitchen to cook plenty of delicious pastries for me daily.
That's good.
You are now a concubine of His Majesty.
You will always need to give priority to His Majesty.
Do you understand?
Um ... May I ask Your Majesty for a tiny favor?
I wonder whether Your Majesty will agree.
Go ahead.
I want to live with Sourire.
I moved out when she was ill, but now
Sourire has been cured for a long time.
I'd like to be her companion.
Living alone in the Palace of Pearl Jade is rather cold and cheerless.
I'd be delighted to have Attendant Chun by my side.
It'd be great if you move back.
It would put my mind at peace if all the concubines
had such a good relationship as you two.
She is moving out?
- Be most careful with Attendant Chun's belongings?
- Yes, yes.
Attendant Chun is young but not dumb.
She "flew to a high branch" in only a few days!
Attendant Chun isn’t that kind of person.
It's just that she likes to live in a lively place.
I'd like that too.
But is it just as simple for me?
Now that she's in His Majesty's favor,
all she had to do is ask.
The Palace of Pearl Jade is small and far off.
It couldn't compare to your palace.
Other than Consort Fleur, no one but
these two are in His Majesty's favor.
Now it's even easier for them huddling together.
Attendant Chun and you entered the palace at the same time,
and you both were recommended by Lady Sourire.
But now she invited Attendant Chun only and not you.
You better ask yourself why.
Lingrong!
Why are you standing here in the cold ?
It was so busy outside that I came to have a look.
I wanted to ask you why you'd bother to move.
This is a nice place and close to the Palace of Pearl Jade.
Sourire and I both like to live in a lively place.
That's why we get along.
Indeed, you two have similar personalities ...
when you come from similar families.
Please go back quickly if you don't feel well.
You're busy. You should go in too.
All right.
My Lady, Her Majesty is here.
Show Her Majesty in quickly.
May peace and grace be with Your Majesty.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
I heard that you got a little cough in the last couple of days.
So I dropped by after visiting Consort Honnête.
It's only a chill from the cold wind, and I had a few mild coughs.
I made Your Majesty worry about me.
You are so young. You ought to take care of your health.
You must not to get ill like Consort Honnête.
That would make my heart ache.
Autumn.
My Lady, this is the Donge ejiao [donkey-hide gelatin]
sent by the Governor of Shandong.
Her Majesty was reluctant to use it herself,
and especially saved it for you.
I thank Your Majesty for your generous favor.
Your palace is chilly in the winter and stuffy in the summer.
Fortunately, the burning charcoal warms it up properly.
I remember when you just moved in,
it was Consort Fleur who had
assigned the residences all by herself.
It was hard to avoid faults.
Don't take it to heart.
With Your Majesty's solicitude,
I dare not ask for more.
I'm content already.
See? You are most modest and polite.
I like you from the heart.
I'm also worried about you.
I'm afraid that you are too unassuming
and being taken advantage of.
That won't happen with Your Majesty's grace.
Is that so?
Your hands are freezing.
Here, lie down quickly.
What's this?
Your Majesty!
All of you, get out and don't talk any nonsense.
Yes, Your Majesty.
This jade pendant ...
I remember Consort Fleur sent one for you
and one for Lady Sourire.
You went as far as to put a curse on this pendant.
Who on earth did you put the curse on?
Consort Fleur? Or Lady Sourire?
Your Majesty.
Lady Sourire and I are just like sisters.
I would die a thousand deaths if I cursed Sourire.
So you cursed Consort Fleur?
How many spare lives do you have to curse Consort Fleur?
And why?
Your Majesty, Consort Fleur humiliated me in every possible way.
She treated me like a maid. I really can't ...
Absurd!
I all along considered you smart and prudent.
I never expected such foolishness from you.
You dare to practice malediction in the palace.
I beg Your Majesty's pardon for my ignorance.
Not only ignorance, this is utter stupidity.
You'd be dead if Consort Fleur saw this!
However, malediction is dependant on evil spirits.
Your fate and your life are in your own hands.
If curses ever worked,
no one in the world would have to use their brains.
I was fatuous.
I wouldn't care about how much you hate Consort Fleur.
But I have to tell you,
instead of racking your brain with curses,
earning favor from His Majesty
will "gain you twice as much with half the work".
Your Majesty, I admit my fault.
You were being silly.
Burn this. I will act like I saw nothing.
I sincerely thank Your Majesty's grace.
You must feel lonely in the palace.
Even though Lady Sourire treats you like a sister,
she cannot attend to everything for you
due to her high status in the palace.
You can pour out your grievances to me in the future.
You must not have any stupid ideas like this.
I shall never forget the great grace
Your Majesty bestowed upon me.
All right. You may rise. It's cold on the floor.
Luckily, someone told me about this.
Otherwise, I wouldn’t have known.
May I humbly ask Your Majesty who it was?
It was your dear sister, clearly.
She had no ill intentions. She just couldn't help.
I have told her that this secret shall never go beyond us.
Was it Sourire?
Stop asking!
Your priority now is to restore your health
and that will make everything easier.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
My Lady, it’s time for medicine.
My Lady …
My Lady!
Traitor!
My Lady, I don’t know what I have done wrong.
Punish me if you will, My Lady.
But I would never dare to betray you!
You are the only one who cleans my chamber,
and the only one who knows what I have here!
How dare you pretend you don't know!
Please don’t be angry, My Lady.
It is my job to clean the chamber for you, My Lady.
But lately you didn’t allow me to make your bed.
I have no idea whether anything is missing or not.
Besides, I'm not the only one who can enter your chamber.
Daisy could too.
If something is really missing, then I'm not the only suspect.
Daisy?
Yes.
My Lady, when you said that you
wanted thicker quilts a few days ago.
It was Daisy who brought them in!
It wasn't a problem. I remembered your order, My Lady,
and asked her to leave away from the bed.
Yes...
There was Daisy.
She was from Sourire’s palace.
Coua, stand up quickly and let me see if I hurt you.
I don’t deserve it.
I’m to blame for such a heavy hand.
But Coua, it was because I trusted you
that I slapped you so badly.
I'd be terrified if the traitor was you!
My Lady, I wouldn’t have the nerve for it.
I’m so relieved it wasn't you.
But I didn’t expect that it would be Daisy.
My Lady, do you suspect her?
She was a servant of Sourire.
There’s no other possibility.
I thought that Sourire had sent her only to take care of me.
I never expected her to put a thorn in my side.
I recall that the Household Department sent two otter fur-lined gowns.
Remember to bring them to Concubine Estime.
One is for her, and ask her to
send the other to Meizhuang secretly .
I will.
I was planning to call on Meizhuang when Concubine Estime is supervising.
But Consort Fleur is watching so closely
that she doesn't miss a thing.
My Lady, please don’t worry.
When next spring starts, you could find a chance
when His Majesty is in a good mood
and ask him to release Meizhuang.
When you get a chance, remember to keep urging my family
that they must capture Liu Ben.
Yes.
Let's go, My Lady.
I heard that the Empress Dowager will also be attending.
Even Lord XVII has returned.
It'd be impolite to be late.
Let's go.
Your Majesty, in this trip, I went to the
ancient plank road from Jiange to Zitong,
and to Dujiangyan [an ancient irrigation system].
I also visited Du Fu's thatched cottage by the Huanhua Creek.
Did you visit the Thousand-Buddha Cliff?
I know Your Majesty is devoted to the Buddha
so I worshipped them one by one on your behalf.
I appreciate your filial piety.
"The road to Shu is harder than climbing to the sky."
[from a poem by Li Bai.]
It must be a difficult trip for you.
Consort Fleur is beautifully dressed today,
Even though I have a poor eyesight,
I can see how dazzling it is.
I thought I must complement the step swing
Your Majesty awarded me with beautiful clothes.
So I ordered some from the Embroidery Department.
Good jewellery must go with good clothes.
That silk flower you're wearing, I can tell, is also priceless.
The flower hairpins in the palace are all made of fabric.
They look pretty but are easy to spoil.
Mine is densely woven with gold thread
and studded with jewels and pearls.
It definitely looks nice. But it must have cost a lot.
I thank Your Majesty for your concern.
After all, my family subsidizes me.
I need not use the palace's money.
If only everyone had a family like Consort Fleur's!
There'd be no need for frugality over the tight monthly stipends.
My family would be nothing without His Majesty's appreciation.
You're Nian Gengyao's only sister.
He would surely pass on anything I rewarded to you.
Your Majesty, it's time for medicine.
The imperial doctor is waiting for you.
I'm not feeling very well. I have to leave now.
Take care of yourself, Mother.
Then I can put my mind at ease.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
This is the wine that Lady Sourire brewed.
Let's all have a taste of it.
This one is osmanthus wine.
This autumn, Lady Sourire and I picked some
osmanthus flowers to make this wine.
No wonder Your Majesty was so proud
when you asked us to try it.
In an imperial feast with so much royalty present,
the osmanthus wine is sweet but seems unremarkable.
Wouldn't the imperial hospitality manifest better if the
guests are served with the treasured wine in the palace?
The war in the northwest has just been quelled.
Since Their Majesties are very frugal,
there is no reason that the harem should differ.
We replaced the precious wine with
the osmanthus wine His Majesty brewed.
This not only shows His Majesty's virtues of thrift,
but also brings the extended family closer.
There's nothing wrong with advocating thrift, Lady Sourire.
But I heard that you have a pair of
jade shoes made with Shu Brocade.
That is so luxurious.
I wonder if I would have the honor to admire them.
His Majesty adores Sourire and awarded her the shoes.
That is why they are expensive and luxurious.
There is nothing wrong with His Majesty's adoration,
is there, Your Majesty?
I appreciate your frankness the best.
What do you think, Lady Fuca?
You are right, Attendant Chun.
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subtitles subscription] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.